# SAMEERUL HAMEED SAHABUDEEN

Address: Forest Gate, London, E7 8AX, Mobile: 07411341045, Email: <a href="mailto:sameerul97@gmail.com">sameerul97@gmail.com</a>, GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/sameerul97/">https://github.com/sameerul97/</a> LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sameerul-hameed-3ab72912a/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/sameerul-hameed-3ab72912a/</a> Portfolio: <a href="https://www.sameerul.com">https://www.sameerul.com</a>

#### **Profile**

A final year Computer Science student who is predicted a 2.1, with experience developing Web applications using HTML, PHP, CSS and JavaScript. As a Masters student, enjoys programming and manages time wisely to complete personal projects outside of academic work. An independent individual who takes ownership and builds strong networks with peers and teachers. Moreover, has been a confident team leader and takes on challenges with a can-do attitude. As a quick learner, has a passion for problem solving and is willing to gain new learning experiences. My target is to look for a graduate/junior position related to Software.

#### **Education and Qualifications**

University of Hertfordshire (UoH), Hatfield

MEng (Hons) in Computer Science

Relevant modules:

• Programming (1st year)

• Algorithms and Data Structures (2<sup>nd</sup> year)

• Computer systems security (3<sup>rd</sup> year)

Leyton Sixth Form, Leyton

• BTEC Certificate in ICT: **Distinction** 

• BTEC Subsidiary Diploma in Law: **Merit** 

• Models and Methods (1st year)

• Computer Science Development Exercise (CSDE) (2<sup>nd</sup> year)

• MEng Group Project (3<sup>rd</sup> year)

Sept 2013- June 2015

Sept 2015- Present

• BTEC Subsidiary Diploma in Business: **Distinction** 

• Financial Studies: C

Little Ilford School, Ilford

8 GCSEs grades B-C (including Mathematics and English)

Sept 2009- June 2013

## **Technical Skills**

Java

• C, C++, C#

• PHP

• HTML

- Linux
- SQL

Git

- Web Service (REST API)
- Python
- CSS
- JavaScript

#### **Other Skills**

- Team work– created good connections with peers and communicated ideas clearly to accomplish university projects
- Time management- managed time efficiently by successfully completing academic projects while doing personal projects.
- Problem Solving- an alternative method was used when attempts were made to improve the position of a draggable button for the MEng Group web application project.
- Flexibility- open-minded to execute new tasks by learning new technology for web application project
- Adaptable- have undertaken tasks within a group environment and individually

#### **Key Achievements**

- Created a web application as Web Freelance for Sahab Solicitors
- Proactive during scrum meeting with Sahab Solicitors.
- Became a team leader during a university project
- Pair programmed when building a web application for a local NHS centre project
- Experiencing and using agile planning in projects at university
- Acquired technical competence with Bitbucket
- Experienced using the entire software lifecycle during team and individual projects

## Relevant Work Experience

#### Web Freelancer, Sahab Solicitors, Ilford

- Created a successful website to inform the types of service available for clients
- Used Linux, Apache server, My SQL and PHP using LAMP Stack framework
- Created a contact form to allow clients to contact the solicitor
- Used PHP Mailer to implement Email Automation
- Created responsiveness and UI by Bootstrap
- Added Custom CSS3 Media query
- Took part in scrum meetings to discuss my progressions
- Link to project: http://www.sahabsolicitors.co.uk

Sept 2017- Jan 2018

When maintaining the project, changes were made:

• Migrated from apache server to Nginx server. Performance of nginx server was better in terms of load balancing as this website was hosted in Raspberry Pi.

#### Other work experiences:

## Casual Sales Assistant, Sports Direct, Romford

July 2017 - Jan 2018

- Dealing with customer's issue's by giving them direct information that reaches their needs
- Tidied shelves in time management for customers to be enticed by presentable stock on shelves
- Worked in teams to undertake various tasks in store, such as stocking
- Serving customers on tills with great enthusiasm and use appropriate body language to satisfy customers
- This was a flexible role that helped me improve my retail skills and also, managed my time appropriately with my university commitment

#### Personal projects

#### Full Stack Web Development

- Currently creating a web application of Evernote or One Note
- Used MEAN Stack, MongoDB, Express JS, Angular 2+, Node JS
- Created the backend RESTful API using Express framework
- Used Postman to test the RESTful API
- Implemented user authentication to enable secure access for user
- Designed the API with JWT (JSON Web Token) to restrict unauthorised access
- Used NoSQL MongoDB as Data house

#### Currency Converter Pro

- Created an Android application which fetches live currency rates from an opensource API known as Fixer.io
- Used Java SDK
- Designed the user interface according to guidelines of google material design
- Used http library from Java SDK to make http calls to the API
- Displayed the fetched JSON data in a presentable manner to the user
- Data displayed are real time
- Programmed to save last used currency by the user in local storage
- Programmed to calculate two currency rates by the user

## GitHub Finder (jQuery)

- Created a GitHub finder application, consuming API provided by GitHub
- AJAX calls are made to GitHub API by attaching appropriate headers and authorisation key in order to successfully authenticate and fetch JSON data
- Hosted the application using Raspberry Pi server
- Used subdomain of my domain
- Enhanced my Linux command line skills as the raspian OS is command line
- Link to project: <a href="http://githubfinder.sameerul.com">http://githubfinder.sameerul.com</a>

#### References available on request